<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King Charls his starre: or, Astrologie defined, and defended by Scripture, &amp;c. With the signification of the comet seen Decemb. 1652. As it hath relation to His Majesty, Charles King of Scotland. / By [Theta]4[1000]IS A'[10]2.</title>
            <author>Evans, Arise, b. 1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84155</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867675</idno>
  <idno type="VID">170018</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240946005</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1482_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208753</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867675</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867675e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 190:E1482[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King Charls his starre: or, Astrologie defined, and defended by Scripture, &amp;c. With the signification of the comet seen Decemb. 1652. As it hath relation to His Majesty, Charles King of Scotland. / By [Theta]4[1000]IS A'[10]2.</title>
                  <author>Evans, Arise, b. 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>[Theta]4[1000]IS A'[10]2 = Arise Evans.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The numerals "1000" and "10" in the author's name are in superscript on the t.p.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 20th"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170018:1"/>
            <p>KING CHARLS his STARRE: OR, ASTROLOGIE defined, and defended by Scripture, &amp;c. WITH The Signification of the Comet seen <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1652. As it hath relation to His MAjESTY, <hi>CHARLES</hi> KING of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>BY Θ4<seg rend="sup">1000</seg>IS A′<seg rend="sup">10</seg>2.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3.</bibl>
               <p>Out of the mouth of Babes and Sucklings hast thou ordained strength, because of thine enemies; that thou mighest still the Enemy, and Avenger. When I consider thy Heavens, the worke of thy Fingers, the <hi>Moon,</hi> and the <hi>Starres,</hi> which thou hast ordained.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:170018:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170018:2"/>
            <head>Who or what am I to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this great work? one of a slow speech, a bruitish understanding, a Child in nature, yea, a very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant in knowledge. Give therefore, O my God, unto thy Servant, an understanding heart, that I may discerne the right: O be thou with me, else what doe I here? For without thee am I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Now <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> had the Learned Pen of M <hi>Lilly,</hi> or any other of those many Artists in <hi>Astrology,</hi> whose yearly judgements are fit testimonies of their ability; I say had any of their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings come to my hands, wherein they had discovered in what an eminent manner this last Comet had signification of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170018:3"/> Majesty King <hi>Charles,</hi> I had beene silent: and therefore have I waited the longer, that I might see most mens judgements <hi>Astrologicall</hi> for this yeare; hoping therein to have found this taske undertaken by a much more able Pen then mine: but finding this great thing generally neglected, and considering that the glory of God is herein very much concerned; who hath shewed a strange and more than ordinary signe unto the Children of men, of what he will shortly bring to passe: and looking on the <hi>Astrologer,</hi> or him to whom God hath given this knowledge, of the effects of the Starres, as bound in duty, to declare his judgement freely, faithfully, and impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (according to the measure of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which God hath given him) unto all the World; that so the knowledge of our omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Creatours Providence might alwayes cover the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea, whose Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power, and speciall providence being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, as it is administred, and signified by his excellent Creatures the Starres, is able to make any man, yea, a very Heathen, or infidell to acknowledge with that of the <hi>Psalmist,</hi> in <hi>Psa.</hi> 19. ver 1. <hi>Coeli enarrant gloriam Dei, &amp; opera manuum ejus annunciant firmamentum.</hi> The Heavens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the glory of God, and the firmament shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his handy worke.</p>
               <p>But before I proceed I shall in this place have a word or two to the <hi>Astrologers</hi> of the time; and that is either they are partiall, <note place="margin">Perhaps they had not the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his said Maje<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sties birth.</note> or else it is from humane frailty (of which I and many more may justly complaine) that they have not in a manner imitated the wise men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. 2.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170018:3"/> 9, 10, &amp; 11. (who no doubt were very eminent <hi>Astrologers</hi> of that time, by whom it pleased God to declare the birth of our Saviour, who knew it by the Astrologicall position of a Starre) in these, or the like words: <note place="margin">This was written when the last repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative governed.</note>
                  <hi>O Parliament of</hi> England,<hi>why stand yee out against His Majesty</hi> Charles <hi>the King of</hi> Scotland, <hi>who is by right your Soveraigne? Why keepe yee his three Kingdomes so wrongfully from him? Why deprive yee him of the right so law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully His: is this your Justice? is this to bring glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God, as yee falsely pretend? Know this, God hath declared unto us his servants by his Creatures, that He will arise to do him Justice, and by His Almighty power will enable him to conquer, and overcome all his enemies: yea, and it shall not be in the power of your humane strength (on which you so much bragge, saying wee have won it by the Sword) to resist him; for wee have seene his Starre,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore we desire you to yeild unto him, and speedily to send forth, beseeching him to come in upon conditions of Peace; for the whole Nation knowes yee have profess'd your selves for Gods glory, and the common good: Therefore we say as you ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your profession, desire him to come peaceably to his Crowne, and enjoy the right so lawfully his; whereunto we doubt not but he will assent. But and if by your delay, and hardnesse of heart yee provoke him to take up the Sword, we shall have much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian bloud spilt; and then may you too late repent, and say, we were hereof timely enough warned, yet were not armed to beat down our fancies, and vaine imaginations; but gave to them the soveraignty of our lives, rather than the many warnings of our Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170018:4"/> and ever mercifull God, first declared unto man by his Word, and Spirit; then by his Workes, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Since they have not done it, let the present go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, take it from me, for I deliver it from the sincerity of my heart.</note> But why do I thus continue, since no man hath laid it to heart to declare this great thing, for even all have neglected it; And behold I, even I the unablest of all, yea, I the unworthiest of all Gods servants have (according to my bounden duty) taken this great task upon me, endeavouring faithfully to communicate it to the World according to the measure of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which God hath given me; in the prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of which, I shall by the assistance of my ever blessed God observe this Method follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<list>
                     <item>1. And seeing it is my first publike <hi>Astrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> judgement, I will principally define what <hi>Astrology</hi> is; and answer those objections, which this ungratefull age hath raised against it, and its Professors.</item>
                     <item>2. And then will I shew you the motion, and scituation of this Comet; and how it hath a signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of a great man to arise, and that this man is King <hi>Charles.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Definition of Astrology, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>BUt first of all before I speake much of it, let me looke into the nature of <hi>Astronomy,</hi> and see what it teacheth, without which <hi>Astrology</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid, and nothing worth: for as by <hi>Astronomy</hi> we are taught how to measure, and finde out the Motions, Scituations, Magnitudes, Distances, Aspects, and Configurations, &amp;c. of those heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies the Starrs: So also by <hi>Astrology</hi> are we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170018:4"/> taught, to judge of their naturall pottent, and signification, as they are Signes of future Events: according to that of <hi>Moses, Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. where the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> after he had created those Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall Bodies, gave them this powerfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission; which he hath sealed with his Almighty strength; and speciall providence. <hi>And let them be for Signes, and Seasons, and for Dayes, and for Yeares.</hi> here therefore note, before I passe this, that as there are foure things specified, wherefore these Heavenly Creatures were created; and as the great Almighty hath commanded them to be (and impowered them to obey his commands) for Signes, Seasons, Days and Yeares; so it will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently follow that the Creatour hath given, or let out so much of his Almighty power, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall providence, on these his Creatures, that they may fulfill his will in this particular (that is) as they are for Signes (or rather more if otherwise, for this word Signes is first named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the foure) as on any of the rest before specified, that is, Seasons, Dayes, or Yeares: which if it be so, then let us consider what an almighty, apparent power, God hath given his Creatures, to performe his will, as they are for any of the three last recited particulars: in which all men, except they be so blinde in nature, as those in judgement (who dayly deny Gods Almighty power in his Creatures, as they are for Signes) will humbly acknowledge, yea, dare not deny but that they are guided by the Omnipotent Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their Creator: as for instance in the Sun; <note place="margin">Dayes.</note> for when hee, in a wonderfull manner, is ascending in our <hi>Horizon,</hi> the day appeareth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170018:5"/> and in his descending the night approacheth. <note place="margin">Seasons.</note> So likewise as he drawes from the veruall <hi>Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall,</hi> towards the Artick Pole, we call this Season the Spring, then making his progresse from the <hi>Tropicall</hi> signe <hi>Cancer</hi> towards the <hi>Autumnall Aequinoctiall;</hi> we name it Summer: And as hee journieth from hence towards the Pole <hi>Antar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick;</hi> this Season we call Autumne, or harvest: And lastly from the time of his departure from the Winter solstice to his returning to the vernall Equinoctiall; wee name it the Winter Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. <note place="margin">Years</note> And when as he departeth from some known point of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and returneth to the same againe, we call this space or intervall of time a Yeare.</p>
               <p>I could have declared by many more infallible testimonies in what an eminent manner Gods power is manifested in his Creatures; but affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brevity, I will conclude with this; for I veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe that there is no rationable man but will confesse, yea, it is so evident that he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but that there is a speciall power, and Divine Providence letted out on this Heavenly Creature the Sun (as on others) seeing he doth thus measure out (by his most wonderfull motion) the <hi>Seasons, Dayes,</hi> and <hi>Yeares,</hi> as I have now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated: Then is there such an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power given him, and them to execute Gods will in these three last particulars, and have they none as they are for Signes, as some envious men have affirmed? Yes verily, as God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to be for foure things specified, and this the first and principle of the foure, <hi>Let them be for Signes;</hi> so hath God given them a speciall,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170018:5"/> and so great a power to do his commands in this, as in any of the other as before is said: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou O man whosoever thou art, that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est their power as they are for signes, dost abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deny the Power of God in them.</p>
               <p>And before I conclude this point I will here demonstrate those furious mens confession, who daily rage against and utterly deny Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power in those his Creatures as they are universally for signes; which is say they, we do indeed believe that God doth sometimes let down his Almighty power on some of his Creatures, as he hath created them for signes (that is) when as the Sun or Moone is Eclipsed, when there have beene strange Apparitions, blazing Starres, Comets, and the like; but that any other of those Creatures should be for such extraordinary signes of things to come, as you say, we cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</p>
               <p>Oh, fie upon such fond Atheisme! is one created for a signe, and not the rest? What God <hi>hath joyned, Let no man put asunder.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore since men so willingly swerve from the truth, let us once more consider the words. <hi>Let them be for Signes,</hi> here's none excluded from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or power to execute it; Let them be, what is't but one, or two, of the Celestiall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures here commanded, and impowered, as these men would have it? Consider, the words are very emphaticall, and takes all in a generall way; let THEM be, that is, let all of them be for signes, &amp;c. what and shall those Creatures be for signes onely on some particular Dayes, Times, or Yeares, as the same men have said? fie upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170018:6"/> those willingly ignorant! marke, are not the words in the present tense, which intimates a continued being? Let them be, that is, let <hi>Them</hi> alwayes, and continually be; yea, let them all, and generally be for <hi>Signes</hi> and for <hi>Seasons,</hi> and for <hi>Dayes,</hi> and for <hi>Years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which I also gather, that as the Sun (as is aforesaid) by his continued, and wonderfull Motion, which he hath from the Almighty power of the Creator conferr'd on him, doth shew <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> rule Dayes, and measure Yeares, than which there is nothing more cleare, for dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience confirmes it, so say I, it is as unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable from this place of Scripture that God hath commanded, and impowered likewise by the same power the Moone, and Planets, yea, all of those Heavenly Bodies by their said continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and wonderfull Motions to be alwayes and continually for <hi>Signes.</hi> What, and is all this great Power, and Divine Providence of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conferr'd on all those his Creatures the Starres, to do his Will in this his first, and principle command, as they are for <hi>Signes;</hi> and is this all in vaine? Are those then Signes of nothing as many men say? Oh horrid unbeliefe! Know God made nothing in vaine, they are the Signes of Gods power; yea verily, they are the Signes of the times, as you may see in <hi>Mat</hi> 16. <hi>ver</hi> 3. In the beginning of which Chapter you shall also finde these following words written, <hi>The Pharisees also with the Sadduces came, and tempting desired Him that He would shew them a signe from Heaven.</hi> 2. <hi>Hee answered and said unto them, when it is Evening yee say it will be faire weather, for the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170018:6"/> skie is red.</hi> 3. <hi>And in the Morning it will be foule weather to day: for the Skie is red and lowring. O yee Hypocrites, yee can discerne the face of the skie, but can yee not discerne the Signes of the times?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marke, when they desire a signe our Saviour answered immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heaven, intimating that they should look there for a signe.</note> Where we may observe, that when as those unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving men came unto our Saviour, and desired of him a signe from Heaven, He (as God being the Creator with the Father and the Holy Ghost of all those Celestiall Creatures, made them for divers uses, and this especially to be for Signes, and that they might execute, and obey his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands herein, hath conferr'd his Almighty power, and speciall providence, all which having plainly declared unto man in his Holy Word; where any (except such willingly ignorant <hi>Pharisees</hi>) this truth might plainly see) answered them thus deriding, and condemning their partiality of judgment herein. <hi>Quando serum est dici dicitis Serenitas erit: rubet enim toelum. Et mane, Hodie erit tempestas, rubet enim coelum triste.</hi> Then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering their great folly, he breakes forth with this vehement Exclamation, O yee Hypocrites, and so goes, on <hi>Nostis discernere.</hi> Yee know how to discerne the face of the skie, that is those lower Elementary Regions, and according to their colour yee give your judgement, and say they are Signes of foule or faire weather. Cannot yee discerne: as if he should have said, what are you alwayes willingly blinde as judicially, so also na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally? Have not yee seene the Scripture and therein found that all those Heavenly Bodies were created to be continually for Signes, and that in a large sence? Was their power then particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, and that it should extend no farther as yee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170018:7"/> have now done? That is to be Signes onely of the weather; this indeed argues your grand Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisy; <hi>But can yee not likewise discerne the Signes of the Times?</hi> Cannot yee likewise foretell, by discerning those signes of Heaven, the condition of the present, or future times: and especially this time of the Messias, this glorious time of the Gospell, this time of the Revelation of Divine truths? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>These things and many more God did foreshew and signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by his Creatures the Starrs, as for instance, by the great conjunction of ♄ ♃ and ☿ in the first Face of <hi>Virgo.</hi> Concerning which part of this signe <hi>Abraham,</hi> in his Booke called <hi>Principum sapientiae,</hi> sayes thus, <hi>Ascendit quoque in prima facie ejus Virgo pulchra, &amp; sui capilli longi, habens in manu sua duas spicas, ipsaquc sedet super sedem unam, &amp; nutrit puerum parvulum ipsum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctando ad comedendumque incitando.</hi> A faire Virgin having long haire also ascendeth in the first Face thereof, holding two eares of Corne in her hand and she sitteth upon a seat, and nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a little Boy by giving him suck, and inciting him to eate. And also by that <hi>Starre</hi> in which <hi>Sybella Tyburtina</hi> shewed <hi>Augustus Cesar</hi> the Image of a faire Virgin, having a Boy in her bosome, saying this Child's greater than thou, worship thou him; was foreshewed the Preaching of the Gospell, the sedition of the people, the Troubles, Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, Warres, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which afterwards likewise came to pass. Here also will I rehearse the Verse to whom (I meane the aforesaid <hi>Sybill) Mantuan</hi> alluding hath written, as they are excellently translated by Mr. <hi>Lilly.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Augustus</hi> with the Senate, People, <hi>All</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fitting themselves for holy mysteries,</l>
                     <l>She hast's from <hi>Tiburs</hi> Tower, comes to the Hall</l>
                     <l>Or Court of <hi>Caesar,</hi> pointing to the Skies</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170018:7"/>
                     <l>Where in a most cleare ayr, she them did shew</l>
                     <l>A Mother and her Babe, wrapt round about</l>
                     <l>In a bright Iris, or most fulgent Bow,</l>
                     <l>Upward her Face and both her hands stretcht out:</l>
                     <l>(Viewing the Child, and poynting with her hand)</l>
                     <l>Who is that Boy? <hi>(sayes he)</hi> O <hi>Cesar</hi> peace</l>
                     <l>Worship thou Him: The Heavens he doth command,</l>
                     <l>The Altars and the Temples now must cease,</l>
                     <l>Leave them to Him He rules the Firmament,</l>
                     <l>The immortall Heavens he orders, and doth guide</l>
                     <l>The fatall Starres; under his Government</l>
                     <l>Are all subjected in the World beside.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Augustus Cesar</hi> let thy haughtinesse</l>
                     <l>Be laid aside, what though thou rul'st the Earth</l>
                     <l>Thou must remember that thou art much less,</l>
                     <l>And art his Vassell, brag not of thy Birth,</l>
                     <l>His power is infinite, and rules on high</l>
                     <l>All things are under his Authority.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For by times is meant all things done in those Times, either Ecclesiasticall, Politicall, or Naturall, both generally, and particularly; both Men, Actions and all other things acted, having dependance on Time. But before I dispatch this I will acquaint you with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Annotations of those Annotators of the Scriptures, who delivered their judgements in two Volumes, which were Printed in the yeare of our Lord 1651. And that is on the word Signes in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>vers.</hi> 14. the words they have written, are these that follow:</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170018:8"/>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="annotation">
                           <head>Annot.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Signes</hi>] Of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as the Sun when it setteth with a red Skie foresheweth a faire day to follow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 2. The Moone according to the variety of its colour and figure signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a difference of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and both of them by their Eclipses be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token the temper of the ensuing Season, at least for some naturall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and events, &amp;c. with abundance of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallitie: See the Bookes.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="interpretation">
                           <head>Interpret.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Here first of all they begin to limit Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power, which he hath extended without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation in these words, <hi>Let them be for signes,</hi> Yet by all meanes these Annotations would have this to be the grosse sum without examining the particulars. <hi>Signes]</hi> of the weather: for which they produce <hi>Mat. 16. 2.</hi> why they might have as well produced the third <hi>ver.</hi> to, seeing it doth as greatly concerne the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have in hand as this; which if they should have done, they had likewise declar'd in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the Verse, that they are also the Signes of the times as I have shewed; but being bent utterly to destroy <hi>Astrology,</hi> they will not by any meanes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Oh the bitternesse of those men! who to make way for the letting out of their envy and hatred towards man; have thus limitted, yea, denied the Power of God: for as our Saviour said, <hi>he that is not for me is against me,</hi> so say I, he that will not confesse Gods Power, denies it. Here, as I said before, was the <hi>Pharisees</hi> hypocrisie, who, by considering the Signes of Heaven, were very well
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170018:8"/> able (according to their naturall signification) to foretell what weather should succeede; but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the mistrust of Gods Almighty power, or from their malitious willing ignorance it was, that they likewise did not, or at least wise would not, strive to foretell their naturall portent, as they are the Signes of the times. But let's proceed, and then we shall finde them confesse something concerning the Eclipses of the Sun, and Moone; which is, say they, Eclipses betoken the temper of the ensuing season, at least for some naturall qualities, and events: Doth the Sun and Moone indeed betoken events, and doth not the other Planets also? Receiv'd not they all alike, one and the same Commission? [but for this farther see Page 9. 10.] for my time will not give leave to examine every particular; and to the places of Scripture, which they bring against <hi>Astrology,</hi> I shall by and by answer when I come to handle the Objections.</p>
               <p>But now let us examine another place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and let that be <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. Where, for wise men, they interpret <hi>Astronomers</hi> (by no meanes <hi>Astrologers,</hi> for they hate them.) But marke, <hi>They which are</hi> Astronomers <hi>alone; doe only measure out the Motions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Starres; and so cannot tell what they signifie (for this</hi> Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers <hi>only do.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Those wise men knew that the Starre, which they saw did signifie that the King of the</hi> Jewes <hi>was, borne,</hi> Ergo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Those wise men were</hi> Astrologers. Which truth condemnes the partiall judgments of those men: well was it said <hi>Envy cannot see,</hi> no, neither here
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170018:9"/> can it discerne the truth, nor many more of those their Annotations on the like places of Scripture, which concerne <hi>Astrology,</hi> any judicious Men may plainly behold the seeds of Envy, which they, by their partiall malitious-wresting of the Holy Scriptures, to serve their own turnes, have appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently discovered; but considering these things are too too manifest, I shall onely in this place desire all those who chiefly aime at Gods glory and his peoples good to take notice of these things, not disdainfully as they are fallen (for in many things we sin all) but exhortingly that they may arise againe; not condemning their persons, but this their Doctrine: and my selfe praying for their Reformation shall immediately proceede on my intended matter, onely by the way will I first give you Mr. <hi>Diodati</hi> (a most learned man and a Minister of Gods Word) his impartiall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the word signes in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. which is, Signes] namely, of naturall effects, as of heat, cold, Raine, faire weather, &amp;c. Signes and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the occasions, and seasons of many hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane actions: also presages of divers extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary accidents.</p>
               <p>And now as I have prov'd and clear'd from Scripture proofes that God hath created, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and impowered all his Heavenly Creatures the Starres to be alwayes, and continually for the signes of the times both present and future, and consequently of all things acted in those times, according to the course of nature; so will I now demonstrate that they are of divers kinds of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and so signifie not all one and the same thing; and also that they are not onely signes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170018:9"/> of future events, but also have a divers kinde of influence, and power from the Almighty to worke or bring what they naturally signifie to an effect, and so consequently are not onely Signes, but causes of what they signifie, under the supreame cause their Creator: which if it were not so, the Scripture would never make a distinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the sweet influences of the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> and the binding vertues of <hi>Orion;</hi> as it is written in <hi>Job.</hi> 38. <hi>v.</hi> 31. Where God speakes to <hi>Job</hi> thus, <hi>Canst thou binde the sweete influences of the Pleiades, or loose the hands of Orion?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation is a vehement negation, and so its, Thou canst not &amp;c.</note> From whence we may note, that God hath not onely given them power to produce their severall effects, whereof they are signes, but also hath said that their influence and power is such under God, that no man on earth is able to unloose or binde it. Much like unto this is that of <hi>Moses</hi> in <hi>Deut. Chap.</hi> 33. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. when as he blessed the Tribes, where you have these words written. And for the pretious fruits brought forth by the Sun; and of the pretious things put forth by the Moone: whence its evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the Sun and Moone have power, <note place="margin">The Sun by heat, and the Moon by moisture.</note> by their severall influences to thrust forth the fruits of the Earth: And likewise in <hi>Hosea,</hi> Chap. 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 21. where God saith that he will heare the Heavens, and that they should heare the Earth, From all which I gather that as the Heavens have power to send forth their influences on the fruits of the Earth: So those hearbes or fruits, according to their natures, do depend on all those starres, or constellations; as they shall let down the power conferr'd on them by their severall influences; And now will I also shew you their power, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170018:10"/> for this see <hi>Judges,</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. where you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly these words, <hi>They fought from Heaven; the Starres in their courses fought against Sisera.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About which time its very consentaneous to reason, there were some who studied this Art, had publickly declared that those Heavenly Bodies, by their divers mutuall Aspects, and configura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were then Signes according to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall signification that <hi>Sisera</hi> should be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in that Battell, the event so truely follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Signe, and <hi>Deborah</hi> considering what an Almighty power God had given those his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that they should thus by their influences, so powerfully worke on, and bring to passe what they were signes of; made her (amongst other her praises of God) breake forth in these words, <hi>E coelis pugnarunt sidera ipsa, è suis aggeribus pugnaverunt contra Siseram.</hi> Many other places of Scripture could I bring forth to strengthen this argument of the Almighty power God hath given them, where they are often said to be the Host of Heaven, but i'le leave it, seeing daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience confirmes it; for as I said before, so say I againe, that the same Almighty power that God hath given them by their wonderfull motion in a most admired manner to bring forth a Season, Day, or Yeare; the very same power is confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God on them wonderfully to shew forth a Signe, and so consequently bring to an effect what they signifie: but know in such naturall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations as these, <hi>agunt, non cogunt:</hi> they doe, yet they do not compell; that is, they do onely incline, or work by their influences, according to their natures on the Elements, and our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170018:10"/> Bodies, &amp;c. whereof they are signes and and see it is not of fatall necessity that such and such things should come to passe, nor do their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences reach any farther into the natures, and naturall actions of men, than to bring them up to an inclination; for God is the supreame cause: (as I have said before) who can as well withdraw their influences as stop, or make retrograde their Motions as he did in <hi>Joshuaes</hi> dayes, <hi>Josh.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 12, 13, 14. And likewise in <hi>Hezekiahs, Isay</hi> 38. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. and therefore in all <hi>Astrologicall</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we ought to conclude thus, these things are like to come to passe; if God, who is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame cause, doth not prevent it.</p>
               <p>Now come I to the Objections, where I shall (by Gods help) handle those especially, which the aforesaid Annotations have raised; seeing they have delivered them so publikely, being Ministers of Gods word; and finding the generallity of men very prone to take their Ministers for an example, and so consequently follow their foot-steps: which is a thing I hold commendable in any, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that they themselves doe trace in truth, and sincerity: therefore will I first begin with this whereon they have raised their strongest argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to overthrow <hi>Astrology,</hi> and that is <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. the words are these. <hi>Thus saith the Lord, learne not the way of the heathen, and be not dismayed at the Signes of Heaven, for the heathen are dismayed at them.</hi> By which and the following words I conceive that the Prophets aime is to roote out Idolatry from the Children of <hi>Israel;</hi> which also the argument in the third, fourth and fifth verses plainly demonstrates: but I will scan the words,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170018:11"/> and give you, by Gods assistance my impartiall judgement of them: Learne not the way of the Heathen, that is, as if the Prophet should say, what and if you and your fore-fathers have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly disobeyed Gods Commandements, and Idolatrously worshipped the Host of Heaven? However, doe so no more, worship yee God the Creator, and not the Creatures; for this is the <hi>way of the heathen;</hi> which were it not so, why should the Prophet immediately after the words bring in this Argument, in the three subsequent verses; but that they, by considering of the Idolatry of the Heathen, might see the vanity of their own: <hi>Be not dismayed at the Signes of Heaven,</hi> that is, be yee not afraid of these your Gods, whom yee have set up unto your selves, to worship them, for I tell yee they are Gods servants, and without his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission have no more power of themselves than those wooden stockes, which the Heathen worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, whose you may see in the latter part of this fifth verse; and because of the concordancy I will rehearse the words, <hi>Be not affraid of them, for they cannot doe evill, neither is it in them to doe good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Heathen are dismayed at them, that is, those men that have not known the true God, but have made Idolls to themselves whom they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; they Idolatrously feare them, thinking there is no power above them. So now have I briefly touch'd at the particulars of this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet have not found a word against the lawfull use of <hi>Astrology;</hi> but it doth teach thus much, that as we confesse, and acknowledge that they are onely govern'd by Gods Almighty power, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170018:11"/> speciall Providence to performe all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; so we ought not to looke on those starres, as absolute Lords; and ascribe to them more than to him that created them, not to the instrument, but to the great supreame Cause, we ought, I say, to ascribe Glory, Honour, and Power. Many things could I alleadge against those Annotations, which they have written on this place <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 2. but seeing they willingly swerve from the truth of Scripture, and to feede their own malitious fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies have erroniously ranted at the pure science of <hi>Astrology;</hi> both without rule and reason: either of which had they produced, I would have answered it, but since they have not, i'le condemn their folly, and resolve not to waste inke and paper about such nicities, whilst an envious tongue hath utter'd it.</p>
               <p>Another place of Scripture, which they produce, is <hi>Isay</hi> 47. <hi>v.</hi> 13. from whence (say they) its cleare that <hi>Astrology</hi> is naught, for God hath derided it: but stay sirs, I hope the Defendant may be heard as well as the Complainant, &amp; therefore I'le open the cause, the words are, <hi>Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy Councells: let now the Astrologers, the Star-gazers, the monethly Prognosticators stand-up, and save thee from those things that shall come unto thee.</hi> I will by Gods assistance declare my truely impartiall-judgement on these words also, by conferring with some of the precedent, and subsequent Verses: first therefore know that these words were chiefly directed, and spoken to the <hi>Babylonians;</hi> which truth you may see in the first verse of this Chapter; And that those men being grosly ignorant of the true knowledge of God the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170018:12"/> Creator, did ascribe all their Acheivements unto, and let out all their confidence on themselves, and others the Creatures; is apparently held forth in <hi>ver.</hi> 7. 8. 10 and this 13. and so it doth conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently follow, that those <hi>Astrologers</hi> here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, being also <hi>Babylonians,</hi> were led by the same Atheisticall Idolatrisme, who when they did deliver their judgements, no doubt did make the Starres such absolute Lords, as by their owne power to bring to passe alwayes whatsoever they signified by their naurall motions: for they, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ignorance, did not know, or believe that there was any power above that did oversway them; nor were they sensible that there was an Almighty Creator, who made them, that could by his power either stop their Motions, or withdraw their influences at his pleasure: and yet are those ignorant Creature-Idolizing <hi>Astrologers</hi> the great Counsell of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Wherefore the great JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH seeing their ignorance, and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their folly, doth in these words speake after this manner, Let now thy great Counsell the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologers,</hi> who are as ignorant in the truths of God as thy selfe, let those I say, in whom thou hast hitherto trusted, stand up, and save thee from these things that shall come unto thee: but behold, as yee have alike swerved from mee, and ascribed all my glory, and honour unto my Creatures; so shall yee alike have the same punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for <hi>they shall be as stubble,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>vers.</hi> 14. All that I can discerne in this place of Scripture is, that every <hi>Astrologer</hi> ought to make the subject matter of his discourse, on the effects of the stars, the praise, and glory of God; and to ascribe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170018:12"/> to the Creatures as done of them; lest God, for doing it charge them with Idolatrisme; and give them this sentence in his anger, <hi>They shall be as stubble, the fire shall burne them, &amp;c.</hi> 14. <hi>Verse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before I dispatch this Objection, let me a little illustrate it with some other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; first see <hi>Psal.</hi> 33. 17. in which and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verse the Psalmist sets forth how unable the strongest Creatures are to put their power in execution, without their Creators permission: as A horse is a vaine thing for safety: neither shall he deliver any by his great strength. So say I, (for I am enforc'd to make a comparison for demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations) sake that is a vaine thing for any man to trust to the <hi>Starres</hi> for safety, though they be an <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 2. vers. 1</note> Host, or to thinke that they by their own power can deliver any man, for I tell yee, they can no more doe it, than those <hi>Astrologers</hi> could the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> in whom they trusted.</p>
               <p>Also see <hi>Isay</hi> 30. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. where you may see how God deales with those who trust onely in Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and not in the Creator: <hi>But yee said, no we will flee upon horses; therefore shall yee flee; and we will ride upon the swift, therefore shall they that pursue you be swift:</hi> so sayes God to the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> seeing ye have reposed all your trust and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence on the Creatures, and taken all your counsell from those <hi>Astrologers,</hi> who are as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of God as your selves: behold I am speedily bringing my judgements upon yee, and then let those, who have beene your Counsellors, deliver you.</p>
               <p>Now consider, because it is said <hi>An horse is a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170018:13"/> vaine thing; And we will flee upon horses, therefore shall yee flee &amp;c.</hi> shall we, I say, therefore altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect, and reject the lawfull use of this Creature? Even so it is with <hi>Astrology;</hi> because God condemning these <hi>Babylonians</hi> for their great and onely rely on Creature-comforts hath deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at their Creature-idolizing <hi>Astrologers;</hi> who acknowledge no God but the Starres, no power above them, and nothing acted but by them; shall therefore the lawfull use of this science be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and neglected? No verily, it was the great abuse God derided it, then <hi>Tolletur abusus, non usus.</hi> Let us remove the abuse and continue the use to the glory of God.</p>
               <p>These two are the strongest Objections these men have falsly raised against the lawfull science Astrology; other frivilous ones there are, which (by Gods helpe) I could very well answer, but pressing earnestly towards the chiefe worke here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intended, I doe for the present willingly omit them. And so I leave it to an impartiall judge to decide betweene us, whether these my weake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours or their Annotations, have most verity according to the true sence of these Scriptures, which I have now handled: whose Annotations on many Scriptures, which concerne <hi>Astrology,</hi> if a cleare sighted judgement did compare with the Originall, I doubt but he would discover much malice and hatred in them: O! sie upon the wickednesse of such men, who will change Gods Word, but they'l make their owne good. And against many of the present <hi>Astrologers</hi> I must te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie they have apparently discovered the seeds of malicious revenge, (which especially breakes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170018:13"/> forth in their yearly writings) against the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Ministry: these things are so far from commendation in either of you, that they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abominable, yea, very detestable; these are the workes of darkenesse, sports for the Devill, and deeds of dishonesty: as you may see in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. on which words one excellently said, <hi>not in Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting and Drunkennesse;</hi> that is to feast the World; <hi>not in Chambering and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> that is to feast the Flesh: <hi>not in striefe, and envying,</hi> that is to feast the Devill. And what will yee, Deare friends, who have continually professed your selves for Gods glory; the one to declare it by his word, the other by his workes: will yee I say shew your selves so impious, as to banquet the Devill? Alas, forbeare! for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare! this is odious in the sight of God and Man.</p>
               <p>And whereas I now understand by the Preface of the aforesaid bookes, that those Annotations were written by eight severall persons, each taking a part: I would have no man to thinke I am so uncivill as to blame all for one, but onely him or they who have thus mishandled the Scriptures as aforesaid; and to such I say, I doe not, because they have been overcome with malitious hatred, either condemne their Ministery or Persons, I leave this to God; yea, I am so far from speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against Ministry, or Ministers, that I really honour them for their workes sake, yea, verily, I have found them instrumentall of working grace; Therefore to the omnipotent Creator be glory, both now, and for ever.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170018:14"/>
               <p>So having thus farre defined, and defended by Scripture proofes this lawfull science, <hi>Astrology,</hi> I doubt not but the same words, which God spake (giving these his Creatures their Commission, <hi>Let them be for Signes</hi>) doth also impower man to study their signification: but if you thinke this not enough take <hi>Psal.</hi> 111. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. where it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly said, <hi>The workes of the Lord are great, sought out of all them that have pleasure therein.</hi> Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this, some there are so busy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitive, that they must needs know who were the first Practisers of this Art; to such I answer. <hi>Josephus</hi> in his antiquities of the <hi>Jewes, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 3. relates that the sons of <hi>Seth</hi> first invented this sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who (because <hi>Adam</hi> had foretold of a two fold destruction of the World; the one by fire, the other by water) engraved in two Pillars, the one of brick, and the other of stone, what they had invented: to the end if that of Brick should be abollished by the overflow of waters; the other of stone should expresse unto men that, which was therein im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed for their instructions. Yea, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Abraham</hi> too was excellently well skill'd in this Art, as appeares in the 8. <hi>Ch.</hi> of the same Booke; where <hi>Josephus</hi> speaking of him sayes thus, <q rend="inline">He therefore first of all did most manifestly Preach; and prove that there was but one God, governour, and maker of all things; and that otherwise if any thing conferr'd, or further'd our felicity, it happened to us, not by our owne workings, but by his holy will. And this observed and approved he, by that which chanceth both in the Earth and in the sea<note n="*" place="margin">Mark.</note>; As also those things which hee saw daily occurre by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170018:14"/> of the Sun, and Moon and other <hi>Starres:</hi> namely, that there was a certaine power that disposed them, and decently administred all things; without whose assistance nothing would be profitable unto us. For which counsell the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Mesopotamians</hi> began mutiny against him, &amp;c. And <hi>Berosus,</hi> also speaking of <hi>Abraham,</hi> sayes thus. After the deluge and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the tenth Generation there dwelt a most just, excellent and upright man, and exercised in the knowledge of the Celestiall Bodies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Josephus</hi> further saith in the 9. <hi>ch.</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> was the first that imparted the sciences of Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick, and the observations of the Celestiall Bodies to the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> who before his coming thither, were altogether ignorant of the same: All which you may see in the aforesaid Booke. And if you looke into the first of <hi>Chro. ch.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 32. yee shall finde it recorded, that the Children of <hi>Issachar</hi> were men that had understanding of the <hi>TIMES,</hi> to know what <hi>Israel</hi> ought to do. So it is likewise said of <hi>Moses, Acts</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 22. That he was learned in all the Wisdome of the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that is their liberall sciences; and especially <hi>Astrology,</hi> for they &amp; the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> were the chiefe Professors of it; which Art God hath derided, and condemned in them, as they made use of it; as is before said, yet you see <hi>Moses</hi> is here commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for it, yea, it is left upon Record; who very well knew how to remove the abuse, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the use lawfully to Gods glory. And also the wise men spoken of in <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 1. unto whom it pleased God to reveal the Birth of our Saviour by a <hi>Starre;</hi> that they were most excellent in this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170018:15"/> Art is very apparent. So now have I clear'd unto you that many eminent servants of God in former ages have practised this Art, but because the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Caldeans</hi> have so long studied it, (for they acknowledged no God but the Starres as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said) And did so Idolatrously abuse it, therefore onely hath the lawfull use of it beene long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and that especially by the ignorant; I could have instanced <hi>Job, David,</hi> &amp;c. but I hasten.</p>
               <p>Thus have I proved from Scripture, that all those Creatures, the <hi>Starres,</hi> were commanded, and impowered to be alwayes for Signes; and that in a large sence, the signes of the times, that is all naturall things depending on time; that they have a divers influence, and Power under God to bring what they signifie to an effect: I have clear'd and remov'd the Objections, which envious men have layd as blocks in the way, which indeed a nimble man might quickly leap over; but I have taken the longer time, endeavouring thereby to make the way so plaine, that the lamest judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may not stumble; and lastly I have brought in some examples both from History and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of those, which have been students in this Art: So having finished the first part, I will by Gods assistance, as eagerly as may be, presse on towards the other, which is the especiall, and chiefe thing hereby intended: yea, the onely cause of my present writing: but this happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be my first publique <hi>Astrologicall</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I thought good to demonstrate what Astrologie is. Now commending this to God, from whence it came, I desire it may tend likewise to his Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170018:15"/>
            <head>Of the Motion, and Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Comet seene Decemb. 1652. and how it hath a signification of a Man to arise, and that <hi>That Man is His MAjESTY <hi>CHARLES,</hi> King of SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> I have hitherto spoken of Signes, onely in a generall way; now will I therefore briefly make distinction: and so they are ordinary, and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Ordinary Signes are the Eclipses of the Sun, and Moone, the conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Oppositions, and Mutuall Aspects, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170018:16"/> Configurations of the rest of the <hi>Starres,</hi> which being celebrated according to their common na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Motions, a man might by calculation easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonstrate ad <hi>Punctum,</hi> for a thousand yeares to come, should the World so long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p>Extraordinary signes are such, which depend not on natures course, and therefote naturall man is altogether incapable to know, or speake of these before they manifestly appeare. Such was that in <hi>Joshua's</hi> dayes, when at Gods command the Sun, and Moone stood still untill the people had avenged themselves of their enemies <hi>Josh.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 12, 13, 14. likewise in <hi>Hezekiah's</hi> time, the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> by his Almighty power did make the Sun, contrary to the course of nature, return ten degrees backward. <hi>Isay</hi> 38: <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And also that famous, and unparallel'd Eclipse of the Sun, which was celebrated at our Saviours death, might well be brought in amongst those Signes of wonder: for the Sun cannot naturally suffer an Eclipse, but when he is in conjunction with the Moone, or as we commonly call it, at the new Moon: but this happening neare the full Moone, (for it was about the time of the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the <hi>Jewes</hi> Passover) the Moone being neare diametrically opposite to the Sun, could not at that time with her darke body interpose between him, and our sight; and so it was not a naturall, but a most wonderfull Eclipse; which when <hi>Dionysius Areopagita</hi> saw, did (being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at so strange a sight) cry out, <hi>Aut mundi Authorem pati, vel Machinam ejus dissolutam iri.</hi> Either the God of Nature suffered, or the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170018:16"/> Fabrick of the World shall be dissolved.</p>
            <p>Here could I also speake of many more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Signes, as of the <hi>Starre</hi> which appeared at our Saviours Birth; of the Comet which <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus</hi> mentions in his Booke of the <hi>Jewes</hi> warre; that hung over <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> by the space of a whole yeare before its destruction: divers other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, and new <hi>Starres,</hi> which have appeared a certaine time, and then vanish away againe; yea, of many strange prodigies, which may very well be reckoned amongst those Signes extraordinary: but ayming at the matter in hand, I will onely briefly demonstrate, and speake of this one, and so proceede: That is the <hi>Starre</hi> which appeared at the Birth of his said Majesty the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> (yea, and by right of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> too; which I doubt not but within a few yeares, God will give him in possession:) concerning which <hi>Starre</hi> those verses hereunder written were presented unto his said Majesties Father, as he was going towards <hi>Pauls-Crosse,</hi> to give God thankes for the safe deliverance of her Majesty the Queen, and the birth of his Son,
<q>
                  <l>Rex ubi Paulinas accessit gratus ad aras,</l>
                  <l>Immicuit medio lucida stella Polo.</l>
                  <l>Dic divina mihi tractans aenigmata coeli,</l>
                  <l>Haec oriens nobis, quid sibi stella velit?</l>
                  <l>Magnus in occiduo princeps modo nascitur orbe,</l>
                  <l>Monque sub eclipsi regna orientis erunt.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170018:17"/> Englished thus by Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>When to <hi>Pauls</hi>-Crosse the gratefull King drew near,</l>
                  <l>A shewing Starre did in the Heavens appeare,</l>
                  <l>Thou that consults with Divine Misteries,</l>
                  <l>Tell me what this bright Comet signifies?</l>
                  <l>Now is there borne a valiant Prince i'th West.</l>
                  <l>That shall eclips the Kingdomes of the East.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Some there are which say that this <hi>Starre</hi> was the Planet <hi>Venus,</hi> others deny it; but whether it was or no I cannot positively affirme, for I saw it not my selfe, nor that or any other <hi>Starre</hi> in five years after the time of its appearance, but yet I gather from the report of some, who saw it, that it was the Planet <hi>Mercury;</hi> which if it were, its very likely it was the Signe of that Prophesy spoken by <hi>Ambrose Merlin, The splendour of the Sun shall languish by the palenesse of</hi> Mercury, <hi>and it shall be dreadfull to the Beholders.</hi> I could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large on this, but consider, any Planet within 17 degrees of the Sun is accounted very unfortunate: And <hi>Mercury,</hi> being the Lord of both the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple Angles, that is, of the Ascendant, and Mid-heaven, was a chiefe significator <hi>Astrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> of his said Majesties Person; who being thus accidentally afflicted by the presence of the Sun-beames, yet miraculously God by his Almighty power did make this <hi>Starre</hi> to shine brightly in the mid'st of Heaven, in a cleare Sun-shine day, which is very contrary in nature. I could give you a large Astrologicall judgement concerning this <hi>Starre,</hi> but seeing I am uncertaine (for I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170018:17"/> heare it by others, who perchance have forgotten the true position of this <hi>Starre</hi> in so long time) whether it were <hi>Mercury,</hi> or no, or any other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, or a new <hi>Starre,</hi> as some have said; therefore will I give no positive judgement hereon, but will for the present passe this also; and poceede to my hereby especiall intended matter, and that is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my judgement on this extraordinary Signe, the aforesaid Comet, as it hath a particular signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his said Majesty King <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of comet</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <label>December. 1652</label>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>And first of all will I speake of the Motion of this Comet, or blazing Starre, with its time of continuance, and that principally according to the most accurate observations of that most excellent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170018:18"/> Divine, and Learned Mathematician Mr. <hi>Ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> and others: whose first sight of it being the ninth of <hi>December</hi> in the Evening, did then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that it was with a <hi>Starre</hi> of the fifth magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the head of the hare, neare 10. Degrees of <hi>Gemini,</hi> having about 39. Degrees South-lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. And againe on the tenth day in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neare about the former time it was seen with a <hi>Starre</hi> of the fourth magnitude, in the 5 degree 40′. of <hi>Gemini;</hi> having South-latitude about 28 degrees: so that it moved in Longitude by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde motion about 4. degrees 20′. in the space of 24 houres; and in Latitude towards the North in the same time full 11 degrees: and in this manner it continually moved, contrary to the succession of the Signes (yet every day slower than other) till it came unto the latter part of the second decade of <hi>Taurus,</hi> which was about the 25. of the same <hi>December;</hi> from which time it vanished, having then about 49 degrees North-Latitude: moving all this time in its proper motion from South and by East, to North and by West, about 20 degees in Longitude, and 88 degrees in Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: whose Diameter also, at the said M. <hi>Ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> his first sight of it, seemed to be about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene inches, but towards its disappearing it was not above seaven, for the outward hare vanishing, the inner part shewed more cleare, though lesse. This is the account which those that could make Observations of the same have given; but I have beene certified from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and other Easterne parts, that many have seene this foure dayes sooner than those Observators, <hi>viz.</hi> on the 5, 6, 7, and 8. dayes of the same <hi>December,</hi> which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170018:18"/> being considered according to its motion by the aforesaid Observations, we shall finde its first appearance was about the latter part of the Signe <hi>Gemini:</hi> yea, and some affirme that they saw it sooner than this also, that is one the first day of the same Moneth, which if it were so, it's likely, yea, very consentaneous to reason, that it began nere the quadrate of the degree of the last great Eclipse of the Sun, celebrated on Munday the 29. of <hi>March.</hi> 1652. which is neare the 19. degree of <hi>Cancer:</hi> but however, were it not so, sure I am, from the infallible testimonies of many, who saw it on the 5, 6, 7. and 8. dayes, that it appeared to them in or neare the last degree of <hi>Gemini,</hi> and so transited that whole Signe, steering a retrograde course till it came about the 19 degree of <hi>Taurus,</hi> and from thence disappeared.</p>
            <p>And this is all I can speake concerning the motion of this Comet, wherefore I shall thinke it convenient in this place, to demonstrate unto you how this Comet hath signification of a man to arise, &amp;c. <hi>Cometes si in</hi> 3. <hi>vel</hi> 9. <hi>loco apparuerit, &amp;c.</hi> But I cannot inlarge, my time requires brevity; And therefore know, that its a received maxime amongst <hi>Astrologers,</hi> that when a Comet happens to be in the third, or ninth Houses of Heaven, in respect of the signe ascending of the revolution of the yeare, in which the Comet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares: that it hath signification of a Prophet, or Great man guided with a more than ordinary power of God, to arise and elevate some Nation, beyond expection, and seeing it is so, then let us examine, in what House of Heaven, this Comet first appeared, according to the Figure erected,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170018:19"/> for that moment in which the Sun entred the first scruple of the Aequinoctiall Signe <hi>Aries</hi> 1652. and wee shall finde according to Mr <hi>Vincent Winges Harmonicon Coeleste,</hi> that <hi>Libra</hi> 23 degree 34′. doth ascend in the first House; on the Cusp of the 9 House doth descend <hi>Gemini.</hi> 18°. 59. through which Signe this Comet transited: but if some object, and say it first appeared in <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> to such I answer that the Signe <hi>Cancer</hi> was also intercepted in the ninth House of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution; all which you may apparently behold, in this following figure for that year.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>horoscope or astrological chart</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170018:19"/>
            <p>Then let us also consider in what House of Heaven this Comet happened, according to the figure of the last great Conjunction of ♄ and ♃, and because of the slownesse of their motions the true Ascendent cannot be found; Therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Method of former <hi>Astrologers,</hi> we will make the very degree of the Conjunction, the Ascendant, and then seeke out the other Houses in order: according to which Method, I must make the Ascendent ♓ 25 deg. 27′. which is the degree and minute of the said Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then will the 15 degree of <hi>Gemini</hi> also ascend on the Cusp of the third House. These two are sufficient testimonies to confirme that this Comet hath signification of a man to arise, who shall be guided by Gods speciall providence; yea, one were enough, but because this is the maine thing intended, farther consider, and you shall finde that at the New Moone preventionall, there did also descend on the Cusp of the ninth House the beginning of the signe ♊. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise at the time of the Sun his entrance into the first point of the tropicall Signe <hi>Capricorne,</hi> and at the full Moone, about which time this Comet first appeared, the middle part of the signe <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> did also descend on the Cusp of the ninth House: by all which testimones its very evident, according to the rule before specified, that this Comet hath in an eminent manner, a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple signification of a man to arise, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now having cleared this point, farther consider, that as this Comet at his first appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance had great South-Latitude, yet alwayes mov'd through Northerne signes. So from it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170018:20"/> may I draw this Astrologicall judgement, that the man, hereby especially signified, both him, and his Ancestors, have been men of eminency, who sprang from an ancient and Royall stock; who was essentially North, but by accidentall position (for I speake Astrologically) was very much South, or by adverse fortune cast so low, that it were impossible, according to mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he should ever rise againe; <hi>but with God all things are possible.</hi> It intimates I say a man, not onely deprived of all his just rights, but also of the priviledges of the Law, and humane aide to recover the same; yea, a forgotten and deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man of the times; <hi>who coming to his owne, his owne received him not:</hi> and more than this, having enemies so inhumane, and uncharitable, that seeing God hath suffered him so long to lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tryall of adversity, that stick not to say; <hi>Persecute and take him, for there is none to deliver him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this Comet contrary to the motion of all other <hi>Starres,</hi> either fixed, or erraticall, did move twice as much farther in Latitude, and that Northward, than in Longitude; it prenotes that this man likewise contrary to all naturall reason, and beyond humane expectation shall be speedily impowered by the Almighty victoriously to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his enemies, who will not submit unto him, and also by Gods assistance to be exalted to such an eminent height of honour, that it shall administer matter of wonder, and amazement to all <hi>Europe,</hi> who considering the Almighty power of God that casteth down to the ground, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth up againe; will undoubtedly breake forth. <hi>Glory to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170018:20"/>
            <p>From the Retrograde motion of this Comet I also judge, that this Man shall make great alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, turne many things topsie turvy, change Laws, settle the Government both in Church and State; and all contrary to that which hath beene formerly, making as it were all things new, both Magistrates, and Government; Ministers, and Ministry; Lawes, Lawyers, Officers, &amp;c. and what not? All which he shall be enabled to doe by the assistance of his ever Blessed God, who hath not onely brought to the birth, but also will in his appointed time give strength to bring forth: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to him, yea, to have onely be given glory, and praise both now and for ever.</p>
            <p>But here will it be required of me, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate how this Comet hath a particular significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his said Majesty King <hi>Charles;</hi> this could I by Gods assistance very well doe, but because I would willingly answer some Objections raysed against the like place in Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Comet; which to doe I must of necessity rehearse the words there specified: and seeing I would be short in prosecuting hereof, for my time hastens; I will onely follow his method, for it is exact: and I looke on <note n="*" place="margin">I could wish with my heart he did not so much run out against the Ministers of Gods Word, nor they against the pure science, <hi>Astrology,</hi> and both without cause; but that they would endeavour as much as in them lieth to live peaceably: and would each of them move only in the <hi>Spheare,</hi> in which the Creator hath set them to his glory, and his peoples good.</note> him as the ablest <hi>Astrologer</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> yea, the onely <hi>Phoenix</hi> of the time: whose words are as followeth.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170018:21"/>
               <q rend="inline">And if we consider or very well observe, what person of quality is now borne, having either relation unto this Comet in the tenth House of his Nativity, or place of the Sun, or Moone; or if we observe the position of Heaven at his Birth in relation either to the Eclips of the Sun in 1652. or 1654. or what concurrence it hath or had with the former conjunctions of ♄ and ♃, or will have with the third Conjunction of ♄ and ♃ in <hi>Sagitarius</hi> 1663. Wee may I say assure our selves that that Man, or the man so qualified by birth shall act his part upon the Stage of <hi>Europe</hi> with so much of Divine assistance, that it will not be in the power of any Prince, King, or Nation to resist him, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And is it so indeed? then let us consider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any of these rules will hold in the figure of the birth of his said Majesty; which if we diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examine, we shall finde that there did then culminate on the Cusp of the tenth House, the latter decade of <hi>Gemini,</hi> in which Signe (as most men say) this Comet first appeared; others upon good grounds say it was concreted in <hi>Cancer</hi> though not visible sooner: but it matters not much to enquire in this place, where it did first appeare, since sure we are that it transited through the whole Signe <hi>Gemini,</hi> and so consequently by the very degree of the <hi>Medium Coeli,</hi> or tenth House of the Nativity of his said Majesty: And this is enough according to the aforesaid rule of Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> to judge that this is the Man; even His Majesty <hi>Charles,</hi> who descended from <hi>Charles,</hi> who was lately by the Grace of God of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defender of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170018:21"/> Faith, &amp;c. I say that he is the man, by this Comet signified according to our <hi>Astrologicall judgement</hi> that shall (as afore is said) act his part upon the stage of <hi>Europe,</hi> with so much of Divine assistance, that it will not be in the power of any Prince, King, or Nation to resist him, &amp;c. But seeing this is the principle thing intended, yea, the very foundation on which I raise this judgement; let me search a little farther, that so I might confirme the aforesaid truth by divers other testimonies; and then shall I also find that at the birth of his said Majesty, the Sun, which is the next herein considerable, was neer the 18. deg. of <hi>Gemini,</hi> through which signe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree this Comet also passed: yea, and farther yet, if we consider the aforesaid time, we shall finde that the Moon at that very instant, was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the latter face of <hi>Taurus,</hi> by which degree this Comet also transited, and then disappeared.</p>
            <p>From all which you plainly see, that his said Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, hath not onely relation unto this Comet in the tenth house of his Nativity, or in the place of the Sun alone, or only of the Moon, but in all three, which is a strong, and prevailable argument to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm my aforesaid judgement, that this is the Man.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if we make farther inquiry herein, we shall find that this Comet also transited by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry degree, wherein was <hi>Caput Draconis,</hi> or the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Node of the Moon, at the houre of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of his said Majesty, which degree of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick is held by <hi>Astrologers</hi> of the nature of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> &amp; <hi>Venus</hi> which is of excellent and very admirable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence. But againe to the Method prescribed, and then in the next place, am I to observe the last great Eclips. of the Sun, neer the 19 deg. of the fiery Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall Signe <hi>Aries</hi> celebrated on Munday the 29.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170018:22"/> of <hi>March,</hi> 1652. and consider what concurrence it hath with the position of Heaven at his said Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties birth: in comparing of which I finde that the very degree of that Eclips, is almost in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Sextile</hi> of the Suns place at the Nativity of his said Majesty. From whence might I truely derive this <hi>Astrologicall</hi> judgement, that as that great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips, had an especiall signification of the subversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Powers, Monarchies, Kingdomes, States, Common-wealths, &amp;c. and also as it signified that the honours of some, of the greatest men of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and other places; were nere Eclipsing, and that all the chief Governours of this Nation espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially▪ should stand on such slippery places, during the effects of this Eclips, that should they step never so little unadvisedly, they might suddenly get an irrecoverable fall. So at last, shall this strange Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tastrophe pincipally, and in especiall manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to his said Majesties honour; who will no doubt ascribe all to Gods glory; by whose assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance he shall be enabled to performe all his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Acheivements.</p>
            <p>And now the next thing successively, is to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what harmony that great Eclips of the Sun, near the 19 degree of the fiery and fixed signe <hi>Leo,</hi> which shall happen the second day of <hi>August.</hi> 1654. shall have with the position of Heaven, at the birth of his said Majesty; by observing of which, I finde that this Eclips will also happen near the partill sextile of the place of the Sun, at the time of His said Majesties birth; which signifies <hi>Astrologically</hi> as aforesaid, that if his said Majesty shall (by Gods assistance) before this time come to his Crowne, and appease home-bred tumults, settling his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in peace, he either personally, or some others
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170018:22"/> under his command, during the effects of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips shall (God ayding him) give Pope and Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a mighty ruine; and all is to establish in love the pure principles of the Protestant Religion, that so all might come to the knowledge of God in truth: for I look on this Eclipse, as a signe sent from God to <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and to their chief Governour the Pope, and other their Governours, who must espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially suffer, during the effects of the same: And seeing this is so, I could wish with my heart that all the <hi>English</hi> Nation would submissively, and that speedily acknowledge, and declare themselves with alacrity of mind to be the subjects, as by right they are, of his said Majesty, that both He, and they may valiantly fight the Lords battells to the utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying of Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I prov'd by many certain, and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible testimonies that this Comet had a principle signification of his said Majesty <hi>King CHARLES,</hi> and that he is that Man, who shall act his part on the stage of <hi>Europe</hi> with so much of Divine assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that it will not be in the power of any Prince, King, or Nation to resist him; <hi>for if God be with him, who can be against him and prosper:</hi> all which I gather from the pure science <hi>Astrology;</hi> as it is signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by this blazing Starre, which I doubt not but God, who is the supream cause, wi l speedily bring to passe.</p>
            <p>But some there are which object, and say, why did not M. <hi>Lilly</hi> likewise particularize that Man, who should be assisted with Gods power as aforesaid; but in an obscure manner only said that he was so, and so quallified <hi>Astrologically,</hi> which scarce any man can understand?</p>
            <p>To answer this I say M. <hi>Lilly</hi> did herein imitate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170018:23"/> the Ancients, who when as they were to deliver a publick <hi>Astrologicall</hi> judgement that would be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the tast of most, did usually publish it in a dark sense, that none but the Sons of art might un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it; knowing that man could not endure to be toucht to the quick, and fearing lest they for sp aking such a truth plainly, should incurre the displeasure of most, and withall suffer an unjust punishment from great ones, who can hardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure reproof: (this indeed I look on as the grand obstacle that men have laid in their own way to keep themselves from knowledge) so likewise as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid hath Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> without partiality, declared his judgement freely after an <hi>Astrologicall</hi> manner to those that understand it, that his said Majesty, <hi>Charles</hi> is the very man signified by this Comet: And very likely it was for the reasons before alleag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he did not declare this truth more plainely, knowing that it would be distastfull to the now greatest of this Nation, wherefore in the conclusion of his <hi>Astrologicall</hi> judgement of this Comets sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, sayes thus;
<q>Video taceoque, sapit qui pauca scribit, plus, qui nihil.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I could have been farre larger in my judgement concerning the effects of this Comet, in a generall way, which shall apparently manifest themselves ere 19 years be expired: but seeing this is no part of my task, and being already undertaken, by that only able man of <hi>England</hi> the said Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> in his <hi>Almanack</hi> for the year 1654. to which now refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you, I shall immediately conclude all, with a few words of humble advise to the whole nation of <hi>England,</hi> but principally to the Lord Generall, and that is <hi>(Right Honourable) that you would be pleas'd (both for your own, and the common good) to bestow
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170018:23"/> sometime in perusing of the books of that eminent saint and servant of God, Mr.</hi> Arise Evans, <hi>who hath publikely declared the truths of God these twenty yeares: for doing of which faithfully, hath he many times suffered from the World, imprisonment, persecution, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rision, scoffing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>whose first and second bookes, the one called</hi> A Voyce from Heaven, <hi>the other an</hi> Echo to that Voyce; <hi>do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare that his said Majesty King</hi> Charles <hi>shall come victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to his Crown, maugre all the opposition man can make against him; for he shall be guided by Gods speciall, and Almighty Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to bring to passe wonderfull matters:</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore the said Mr.</hi> Evans <hi>(having by Gods assistance) declared all this, did humbly desire your Honour, and the generality of this Nation, to send forth to his said Majesty, beseeching him to come peaceably to his Crown; for God, saith he, shall give it him, and if he come by the Sword, we shall have much bloud spilt, and yet at last he shall prevaile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But seeing none have hearkned, yea, even all have stopped their Eares at this wholesome Counsell, therefore the said Mr.</hi> Evans <hi>according to his bounden duty hath published a third Booke, which is called</hi> A bloudy Vision. <hi>Wherin he relates that God doth signifie by that Vision, that this sad distracted Nation is once againe to suffer by the Sword, if there be not speedily a peace made with His said Majesty, that so he might re-enjoy all his just rights peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, which God hath given him by inheritance, and now will give him in possession: that so be might be his faithfull Steward. What? and will yee not yet hearken to this neither? will yee still cry Peace, Peace, when behold the Lord hath said,</hi> except yee doe this there shall be no peace? <hi>Oh! Deare Sirs, receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, it will be for</hi> YOUR <hi>good: what and if some world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings have beene pleased to account the said Mr.</hi> Evans <hi>but a pseudo Prophet, I hope you do not so; consider, hath any of his writings, or Predictions hitherto prov'd him so? hath not God been pleas'd to bring to passe this twenty yeares whatsoever be before had signified by this Man? Alas! what former Prophet was there, which suffered not the like Buffetings, Aspersions, Vilifyings and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170018:24"/> Scoffings from man; and doth not this likewise argue him to be a true Prophet of God? But seeing none of these prevalent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will serve the turne, God hath at last shewed a marvelous Signe, to confirme the aforesaid truth by a</hi> Starre, <hi>and that a wonderfull one, whose signification also God hath enabled me (who of my selfe am most unable) to deliver to all men publickly, which is, that His said Majesty</hi> CHARLS, <hi>shall be impowered by God, marvelously to overcome all his Enemies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which, if I have not derived from the pure Principles of Art, ask the learned</hi> Astrologers, <hi>and let them prove if they can that I have dealt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially; or rather testifie with me that they sincerely believe that I have done this truly, and onely to set forth Gods glory, and for his peoples good, that right may take place which indeed is alone my aime: O then consider, and seriously ponder how mercifull our God is, who never strikes before he gives warning; yea, wonderous mercifull to</hi> England! <hi>who hath given divers and many war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to it, first by his Word and Spirit, and now at last by his Workes, that if its present Governours do not willingly, and that speedily remove oppressions from the Widdow, and Fatherlesse, and according to justice give every one his; and particularly to his said Majesty his three Kingdomes, which they have wrongfully and a long time kept from him: He, even our God will arise, to execute right judgement; That as by the Sword they have unjustly with-held his Right, so by the Sword, even another warre) shall he victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously recover the same. Oh! a sad spectacle will it be indeed, to see more Christian Bloud shed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then</hi> (valiant Sirs) <hi>as God hath lent you the Government of this Nation for a time, so I beseech you be good in your Office: have you not solemnly professed your selfe for Gods glory, and the common good? O as you tender your profession do this, that is, set the</hi> KING <hi>on his Throne peaceably; for God hath given you power to doe it, and thereby shall you evidence to the World that your word, and your deed is one, that your professions, and actions do agree in discharging your duty towards God, seeing he will have this man to govern, to set forth his glory; and towards man, in that you shall hereby save many mens lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170018:24"/>
            <p>And O <hi>London! London!</hi> learn in this thy day the things that belong unto thy peace; open thy gates wide that the King may peaceably enter in: let all thine inhabitants abide quietly in their houses, not offering to lift up their hands against him: but unanimously say, <hi>blessed is he that commeth in the Name of the Lord: God save the King:</hi> but I am afraid mens hearts are so hardened, (either from the mistrust of Gods power, not to bring this to passe, or from their fruitlesse hopes of future secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) that they will stand at a distance as long as they are able, and as it were draw down Gods judgements on themselves; and then will he execute his venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them, who have unmercifully shed innocent bloud. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gemini</hi> is the ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>London,</hi> through which this Comet tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited.</note> O learne then to be a <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and be no more go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by thy vaine thoughts, <hi>least at last they be thy destruction; but speedily go forth to the King lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy former actions, and I doubt not, but thou shalt finde the King of</hi> England <hi>a very mercifull King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now also do I desire ye, the whole Commonalty, out of the true affection I bear you; that you (as you render your lives and estates) would not lift up an hand against your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne <hi>Charles;</hi> for God hath shewed, that he shall overcom, and therefore submit unto him in all things, for God will be with him. O dear Sirs, have a care how you fight against <hi>God,</hi> against justice, against the right; none ever did it and prosper: but if yee will still delight in discord, ye shall have your fill of war, and at lest be shamefully conquered: O rather strive to be at concord with your <hi>King;</hi> how can ye expect, but daily to be devoured with wild beasts, as long as ye stand at a distance with your Shepheards? How can ye ever think to be eas'd of the burthens of your task masters, as long as ye willingly abide under the dominion of <hi>Pharaoh?</hi> in a word, how can ye hope ever to be freed from those oppressive Taxes, and greivous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, before you fly to the King, whom God hath ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be your Shepheard: who will have as much care of your lives and estates, as of His own? Speedily then declare your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170018:25"/> selves for him; and he shall conquer all your enemies for you; yea, under his Dominion shall you live in Peace.</p>
            <p>Thus by the Divine assistance have I discharged my duty in publishing these truths, and now do I commend them to all the <hi>English</hi> Nation, to receive instruction from them, but withall I humbly desire all men that they would by no means look on me, as though I do hereby intend to advance my private for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, by publishing it; I tell you, and God can witness it, I am not to receive any p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ivate benefit by it. Therefore seeing it is chiefly for your instruction, and that you may by considering of it give glory to God, this shall be much more prevalent to convince you that I do declare this truth from a sincere heart. <hi>That King</hi> Charles <hi>shall victoriously overcome all his enemies, and that it will be your best way to submit unto him peaceably; otherwise he will make you submit enforcedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>horoscope or astrological chart</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170018:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>